<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the way to life, deuided into three partes The first part sheweth howe, by sinne wee haue deserued Gods curse. The second parte sheweth me, howe wee are freed from the curse, and the law satisfied. The thirde part teacheth vs, what duetyes and thankefulnesse we owe to the Lorde, for this benefite of our redemption.</title>
            <author>B. A., fl. 1580.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09734</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118831</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854038</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854038</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19444</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09734)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19444)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 575:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the way to life, deuided into three partes The first part sheweth howe, by sinne wee haue deserued Gods curse. The second parte sheweth me, howe wee are freed from the curse, and the law satisfied. The thirde part teacheth vs, what duetyes and thankefulnesse we owe to the Lorde, for this benefite of our redemption.</title>
                  <author>B. A., fl. 1580.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Dawson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1580?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signed on B8v: B.A.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Treatiſe of the way to life, deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>into three partes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt part ſheweth howe, by ſinne wee haue deſerued Gods curſe.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde parte ſheweth me, howe wee are freed from the curſe, and the law ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>The thirde part teacheth vs, what duetyes and thankefulneſſe we owe to the Lorde, for this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at <hi>London by Thomas</hi> Dawſon.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:2"/>
            <head>¶ The firſt part ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>our miſerie, and how</hi> by ſinne we haue deſerued <hi>Gods curſe, and eternall damnation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi> TO whom doeſt thou profeſſe thy ſelfe to belong?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> To the liuing God<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 1.1. Act. 14.15.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of heauen &amp; earth: whoſe<note n="b" place="margin">Ephe. 2.10.</note> workmanſhip I am, for that hee hath made and created me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Wherefore hath God created thee?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That I might ſerue to<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 1.4.5.</note> his glorie, by doing his will in<note n="b" place="margin">Ephe. 4.24.</note> righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and holineſſe all my life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Did God then create man that he could doe his will?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea verily, for he created man<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 1.27.</note> to the likeneſſe of his owne image, in true<note n="b" place="margin">Col. 3.10. Epheſ. 4.24.</note> holineſſe and righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Canſt thou then of thy ſelfe doe his will, and keepe his lawe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Nothing leſſe, for in<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 5.18.</note> Adam we
<pb facs="tcp:19444:3"/> are all fallen from the ſtate of innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and<note n="b" place="margin">Epheſ. 2.3.</note> are by nature the children of wrath,<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 3.23.</note> and voyde of all grace,<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 6.20.</note> &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is ſinne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the breach<note n="a" place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.4.</note> or tranſgreſſion of Gods lawe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is the reward of ſinne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Eternal<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 6.23. Mat. 25.41.46.</note> death and damnation both of body and ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How commeſt thou to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſinne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 3.20. &amp; Rom. 7.7.</note> the lawe of God whiche I finde my ſelfe not able to performe, &amp; therefore am guiltie of death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is the lawe of God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a rule of perfect obedience,<note n="b" place="margin">1. The. 4.1.3</note> teaching vs howe to walke &amp; pleaſe God, conteyned in the ten commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Rehearſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 22.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> God ſpake and ſaid: <hi>I am the Lord thy God, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What meaneth this Preface: <hi>I am the Lord thy God which brought thee out of the lande of Egipt, out of the houſe of bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I note firſt, that God ſetteth down his authoritie before his law ſaying: <hi>I am the Lord,</hi> mouing vs to feare him alone: ſecondly, adding <hi>thy God,</hi> hee geueth foorth moſt louing promiſes of his mercies concerning this life, and the life to come, to moue vs to loue him alone, and truſt onely in him: thirdly, repeating his benefites, he addeth mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of faith and thankfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How is this lawe deuided?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 22.37 39. Luke 1.75 1. Table.</note> two principall heades,<note place="margin">2. Tables.</note> or tables.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is conteyned in the firſt table?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Luke 1.75. Mat. 22.37. Ephe. 4.24.</note> Holineſſe, or the true woorſhip of God, commonly called our duetie to God, conteyned in the firſt foure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What teacheth the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement: <hi>Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods before me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It teacheth vs to honour<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 6.4.</note> God alone, that is to worſhip him with<note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 10.12 20.</note> feare, to beleeue in him, and call vppon him through faith, and teſtifie our<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 6.5. Marc. 11.30.</note> loue toward him with thankeſgiuing, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:19444:4"/> our<note n="d" place="margin">Luke 10.27.</note> ſoule, hearte, minde, and thoughtes, conſecrate vnto God, and forbiddeth vs to<note n="e" place="margin">Deut. 18.9.10.11.</note> heare falſe teachers, or to regard ſorcerers, witches, or anie ſuch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What teacheth the <hi>2.</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, <hi>Thou ſhalte not make to thy, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It teacheth vs that wee ſhoulde not liken God to<note n="a" place="margin">Leuit. 26.1.</note> any creature what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, nor woorſhip him in any ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, neither after our o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e phantazie, or by good intentes, not grounded on his worde, but onely<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 4.23.</note> in ſpirite and trueth, after the true<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 12.32.</note> rule of his worde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What teacheth the third com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It forbiddeth vs to<note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 5.7.</note> ſweare be any creature whatſoeuer, or by Gods name<note n="b" place="margin">Leuit. 19.12</note> falſely or<note n="c" place="margin">Eccle. 19.1.</note> raſhly, but in<note n="d" place="margin">Iere. 4.2.</note> truth, iudgement, and iuſtice, with all<note n="e" place="margin">Deu. 4.8.58</note> reuerence of his name, and chargeth vs with the care<note n="f" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.31. Col. 3.17.</note> of gods glorie in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ſpeaking &amp; thinking of his worde &amp; works, and in all our doings.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What teacheth the fourth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement: <hi>Remember thou keepe holy the Sabboth, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We are taught to<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 20.7.</note> aſſemble to heare Gods worde, and vſe his ſacramentes with<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> faith and<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 3.2.6</note> repentaunce, and to pray to him alſo to<note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 56.2 &amp; 58.13.</note> reſt from ſinne, and our owne wayes, to profite in true mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification and ſanctification<note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 31.13</note> whiche God worketh in his Saintes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> It ſeemeth then that theſe foure preceptes teache the true ſeruice due to God, now tell me what is taught in the ſecond table?<note place="margin">The 2. Table.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſecond table teacheth vs<note n="a" place="margin">Luke 1.75 Mat. 22.39 Ephe. 4.24</note> righteouſneſſe, or our duetie to men in the Lorde, conteyning the ſixe laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What learne we in the firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: <hi>Honour thy Father, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We learne to feare, loue,<note n="a" place="margin">Leuit. 19.3</note> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey our Parentes,<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 22.28</note> Princes,<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.2</note> Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, teachers,<note n="d" place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.12</note> Paſtours, Maiſters and<note n="e" place="margin">Leui. 19.32</note> Elders, and all our betters. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, it teacheth all ſuperiors to be as fathers to their inferiours, &amp; the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours to obey in the Lord.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What teacheth the ſixt commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Thou ſhalt doe no murther, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It teacheth vs to ſhun al occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of diſcord, in thought, deed, and worde, all quarrelling, fighting,<note n="a" place="margin">Leuit. 19.17 18. 1. Iohn 3.15</note> hatred, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of reuengement, and teacheth to do<note n="b" place="margin">Mat, 5.43.44.</note> good to all men, euen to our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What teacheth the ſeuenth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement: <hi>Thou ſhalt not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adultry?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It forbiddeth all<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 5.3.</note> fornication,<note n="b" place="margin">Leuit. 18.12</note> vnorderly, and wanton luſts,<note n="c" place="margin">Ephe. 5.4.</note> talkes &amp; ſongs, proud<note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 11.12</note> apparrell, lechery, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, exceſſe and<note n="e" place="margin">Ezec. 16.49</note> idleneſſe. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all occaſions leading to vncleannes, &amp; requireth all ſoberneſſe, chaſtity, and temperancie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What teacheth the eight: <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It forbiddeth all<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 25.14 17.</note> deceite,<note n="b" place="margin">Ier. 8.10.15</note> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe &amp;<note n="c" place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.6.</note> iniury in any dealing, &amp; in all callinges, and commaundeth all true &amp;<note n="d" place="margin">Leui. 19.13.</note> iuſt dealing in iudgement, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, &amp; weight, &amp; teacheth euerye man to bee content with his eſtate<note n="e" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.28.</note> and to helpe others.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What teacheth the nienth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement: <hi>Thou ſhalte not beare falſe &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It forbiddeth all<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 23.1. Pſal. 15.3.</note> hearing, and<note n="b" place="margin">Leui. 19.16.</note> ſpeaking of ſlaunders and vntruthes againſt our neighbours, all flattering, lying, vpbrayding, and diſſembling, and chargeth vs with the care of the good name of our neighbour, and charitablie to witneſſe the truth to the eſtabliſhing of loue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What teacheth the tenth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement: <hi>Thou ſhalte not couet thy, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It teacheth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not only a conſent to the deſires of euill, is ſinne, but the motion of ſinne it ſelfe is againſt Gods<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.7. &amp; 7.7. Gal. 5.17.</note> lawe, and bewrayeth our concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and conuinceth vs of the breach of the lawe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Sith then that wee cannot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the law, to what vſe ſerueth it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſhewe<note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 3.19</note> man his weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 3.20 &amp; 7.7.</note> accuſe and condemne man, and maketh the faithfull to<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 3.24</note> flee to Chriſt, and acknowledge the free grace of God to bee the onely cauſe of their
<pb facs="tcp:19444:6"/> health, it increaſeth the knowledge of Gods wil in them,<note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 2.16.19</note> humbleth the fleſh, and ſtirreth vp the ſpirite to<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 8.10.11</note> obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by Gods ſpirite, whiche maketh the lawe<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 19.17</note> profitable &amp; ſweete to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>The ſecond part teaching <hi>how we are freed from the</hi> curſe, and the law ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> BY what meanes then is the law ſatiſfied, and this curſe anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God of his infinite<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 3.16</note> loue, in the<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 4.4.6</note> fulneſſe of time, ſent his ſonne made of a woman, and ſubiect to the law, and redeemed vs from the ſlauerye of it,<note n="c" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.19</note> reconciling vs to God by not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting our ſinnes vnto vs, and ſo was<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8.3.4 2. Cor. 5.21</note> made ſinne for vs, that we in him might be righteous before GOD, and ſo<note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 3.13</note> freed from this curſe, and the law ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> It ſeemeth then that we obtayne
<pb facs="tcp:19444:6"/> not righteouſneſſe by the law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No verily, but<note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 2.16. &amp; 3.11.12.</note> by fayth in Ieſus Chriſt,<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 15.6 Rom. 4.13.16</note> in whom our faith is counted for righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is faith then?</p>
            <p>A: It is a certaine<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 4.13. 1. Ioh. 5.23</note> knowledge &amp; ſure<note n="b" place="margin">Mar. 11.22</note> perſwaſion of the free good will of God towardes vs in Chriſt,<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 8.10</note> ſealed in our hearts by his ſpirite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How come we by faith?</p>
            <p>A. By<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 17.8.20 Rom. 10.17</note> hearing the worde of God preached.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Haue we faith then by bare hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the word?</p>
            <p>A. No, but it is the<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 6.44 Ephe. 6.23. &amp; 2.8. Phil. 2.13</note> woorke of Gods ſpirite in vs.</p>
            <p>Q. Is faith then needfull?</p>
            <p>A. Yea,<note n="a" place="margin">Mar. 16.16 Iohn. 8.24</note> for without faith we cannot be ſaued.</p>
            <p>Q. What profit then haue wee by faith?</p>
            <p>A. Wee are<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 3.23. &amp; 5.1.</note> iuſtified thereby &amp;<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 1.12. Gal. 3.26.</note> made the ſonnes of God.</p>
            <p>Q. Rehearſe the ſumme of this thy faith?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>I beleeue in God the Father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie. &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:7"/>
            <p>Q. What is the briefe ſumme of all this?</p>
            <p>A. I learne foure thinges: firſt that God<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 1.1 Ephe. 4.6 Deut. 32.58 Mat. 2.10.</note> the father is creatour and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of al things in heauen &amp; earth. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that God the ſonne<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.17 Gal. 4.5. 1. Ioh. 2.12</note> is redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of the world. Thirdly, that God<note n="c" place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.13 1. Pet. 1.2.</note> the holy Ghoſt is the ſanctifier of his people. Fourthly, that by this meanes GOD hath<note n="d" place="margin">Ephe. 5.26</note> purchaſed to himſelfe a Churche, and made it holy to ſerue his glory in life</p>
            <p>Q. Are there three Gods that thou nameſt, God the father, God the ſonne, and God the holy Ghoſt?</p>
            <p>A. No verily, but<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 4.6</note> one onely eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God, in one eſſence and being, yet<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 4.16.17. &amp; 28.19 1. Iohn 5.7</note> diſtinguiſhed in three perſons, becauſe of their ſeuerall operations, effects and properties.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. part.</note>Q. Why is the firſt perſon in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie called father?</p>
            <p>A. Becauſe hee hath<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 1.1.</note> created all things, and<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 20.17. 1. Iohn 3.1.</note> adopted the faithfull to be his children in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. Why is he ſayde to be almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:7"/>
            <p>A. Becauſe his power is ouer all thinges, and ruleth them all by<note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 10.13. He. 1.3. &amp; 11.3 2. Pet. 3.5.6</note> his word.</p>
            <p>Q. Why is he called maker of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth?</p>
            <p>A. Not onely becauſe he made hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, and all thinges in them, but alſo becauſe hee<note n="a" place="margin">Eſay. 40.26. Ier. 10.12.13</note> ordereth, and<note n="b" place="margin">Eſay 42.5.</note> preſerueth them all by his prouidence.</p>
            <p>Q. What followeth in the ſecond article,<note place="margin">2. part.</note> 
               <hi>and in Ieſus Chriſt his onely ſonne our Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Here beginneth the hiſtory of our redemption, wrought by the ſecond per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in trinity, God the ſonne.</p>
            <p>Q. What ſignifieth this worde <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It ſignifieth<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 1.21</note> a Sauiour.</p>
            <p>Q. VVhy is Chriſt called a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour?</p>
            <p>A. Becauſe hee<note place="margin">Mat. 1.21</note> ſaueth his people from all their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Q. What doeth this worde <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſignifie?</p>
            <p>A. It ſignifieth annoynted, and is ſo called becauſe hee was annoynted with<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 45.7 Ioh. 3.34.</note> the holy Ghoſt, to bee the<note n="b" place="margin">Luke. 1.32</note> king,
<pb facs="tcp:19444:8"/>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 110.4 Heb. 4.14.</note> prieſt and<note n="d" place="margin">Luke 24.10 Heb. 1.2</note> prophet to GOD his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Q. What is his kingdom?</p>
            <p>A. It is ſpirituall and<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 18.36</note> heauenly, wherby he gouerneth his church by his word and ſpirite, and<note n="b" place="margin">Col. 1.13 Heb. 2.14</note> triumpheth ouer Satans kingdom in<note n="c" place="margin">Col. 1.22 Heb. 1.3 1 Pet. 2.24</note> his owne perſon for vs.</p>
            <p>Q. What profite haue we by his kingdome?</p>
            <p>A. We haue<note n="a" place="margin">Luke 1.71.74. Rom. 8.2.15</note> libertie of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, regeneration,<note n="b" place="margin">Ephe. 6.16 Apoc. 12.11</note> ſtrength and vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie againſt Satan, death, hell and ſin, and finally, are made<note n="c" place="margin">Ephe. 4.7.8.</note> partakers of Chriſt his graces and ſpirituall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <p>Q. Why is he called a prieſt?</p>
            <p>A. Becauſe he was the<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 2.17 &amp; 9.11.12</note> true high prieſt, to offer his own bodie a ſacrifice for our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Q. What doth his prieſthoode pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite vs?</p>
            <p>A. It aſſureth vs that he is our<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.24 Heb. 7.25</note> mediatour, to reconcile vs to God, and ſatiſfie for our ſins, &amp; to<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 5.2 Ephe. 2.18</note> make an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for vs, to come<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 8.15</note> before our God with boldnes, to pray to him, &amp;<note n="d" place="margin">Heb 13.15 1. Pet 2.5</note> offer
<pb facs="tcp:19444:8"/> ſpirituall ſacrifices.</p>
            <p>Q. Why is he called a Prophet?<note place="margin">Eſay 55.4 Heb. 1.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. Becauſe he is the full inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter of his Fathers will vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Q. VVhat profiteth it vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue this?</p>
            <p>A. Much verily: for hereby our faith is ſtayed on the<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 3.33.34 Heb. 1.2. &amp; 2 3</note> doctrine of Chriſt, ſo that we looke for no other doctrine or reuelations then his goſpell though<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> reuealed from heauen by an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell.</p>
            <p>Q. Sith thou calleſt Chriſt the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne of GOD, howe is it that the faithfull are alſo the ſonnes of God?</p>
            <p>A. Chriſt is onely the ſonne<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 1.18. &amp; 3.16.</note> of God by nature,<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 4.5.6. Ephe. 1.5</note> the faithfull by grace &amp; adoption in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. Why is he called our <hi>Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Becauſe he is the<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 1.22. &amp; 4.15. Col. 1.18</note> onely head of his Church, and<note n="b" place="margin">Apoc. 17.14.</note> ruler of men and Angels, and we are aſſured of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p>Q. What teacheth the <hi>3.</hi> Article: <hi>whiche was conceiued by the holye Ghoſt, borne of the Virgin Mary?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:9"/>
            <p>A. It teacheth that as Chriſt was<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 9.5 Col. 2.9.</note> perfect God, ſo hee was alſo perfect<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 5.25.</note> man<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 4.4.</note> borne of a woman, yet by a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſeede, that hee may<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 2.11.</note> ſanctifye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Q. Was it needfull that he muſt be both God and man?</p>
            <p>A. Yea, or els he could not be a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour for man, for the<note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 2.9.</note> godhead dwelt in him bodily, that ſo in<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note> our nature, he might by death deſtroy the power of Sathan and ſinne, and<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> beare our curſe.</p>
            <p>Q. What profite haue we by his manhood?</p>
            <p>A. Chriſt therein diſcharged vs<note n="a" place="margin">He. 2.14.17</note> of his fathers anger, and in taking our nature,<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 1.16. Ephe. 2.5.6.</note> parteth to vs his graces.</p>
            <p>Q. VVhat learneſt thou in the fourth article: <hi>He ſuffered vnder Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate, was crucifyed, dead, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried: hee deſcended into hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. We learne what anguiſh of death Chriſt the<note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18.</note> iuſt ſuffered on the croſſe for vs that are vniuſt, that we might be healed<note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24.</note> by his ſtripes.</p>
            <p>Q. Wherefore did Chriſt thus
<pb facs="tcp:19444:9"/> ſuffer and die?</p>
            <p>A. For our<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 4.2.6</note> ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Q. What profite haue wee by his death?</p>
            <p>A. The<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 1.7</note> forgiueneſſe of our ſins, the<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 6.5</note> mortification of our fleſh, and<note n="c" place="margin">Col. 1.20</note> the appeaſing of Gods wrath.</p>
            <p>Q. What meaneth his deſcending into hell?</p>
            <p>A. Euen this, that for a time<note n="a" place="margin">Eſay 53.3.5</note> he felt his fathers wrath, and the<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 2.24</note> dolours of eternall death in his<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 26.38 42 Luke 22.43. Heb. 5.7</note> ſoule and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence here on earth, that hee might bee a redeemer as well of the ſoule as of the bodie.</p>
            <p>Q. What teacheth the fifte Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle: <hi>the third day he roſe againe from the dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It teacheth that Chriſt<note n="a" place="margin">Col. 2.15 Heb. 2.14 1. Cor. 15.57</note> ouercame death, and brake the kingdome of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than for vs.</p>
            <p>Q. What vſe haue we of his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection?</p>
            <p>A. Wee haue<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 9.25</note> iuſtification, a<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.20.22</note> gage of our immortality, and<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 6.4</note> newnes of life.</p>
            <p>Q. How art thou aſſured that thou
<pb facs="tcp:19444:10"/> art in Chriſt, and haſt part in his death and reſurrection indeede?</p>
            <p>A. By this, that<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.9 2. Cor. 5.5 1. Iohn 4.13</note> God hath geuen me of his ſpirit, which<note n="b" place="margin">Ro. 8.10.11</note> ſubdueth ſinne in me, and ſo<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 8.13. &amp; 6.6</note> mortifieth my fleſhe, bringing mee in hatred with ſinne and Sathan, and for that I feele<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 6.4</note> ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and a new life to be begunne in me by his reſurrection, which certifieth my conſcience, that I am in Chriſt, and ſo of God.</p>
            <p>Q. It ſhould ſeeme then, whoſoeuer taſt not at all of true<note n="a" place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.3.6</note> mortification, and newneſſe of life, howſoeuer otherwiſe boaſting of the mercies of God, of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes death, and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes by him, yet hath hee no part in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>A. It is very true, for as<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 4.25</note> Chriſt dyed for our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our righteouſnes, ſo he reſtoreth ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to the faithfull<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 6.6.18 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pet. 2.24.</note> to ſubdue ſinne in ſome meaſure, and to walke in a new life and righteouſnes here on earth.</p>
            <p>Q. Nowe tell me what followeth in the ſixt article: <hi>Hee aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth on the right hande
<pb facs="tcp:19444:10"/> of God &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. We learne that Chriſt hauing accompliſhed, all that was needefull for our ſaluation, went into<note n="a" place="margin">Mar. 16.19 Act. 1.9</note> heauen with his body, and<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 10.12</note> ſtayeth there til he come to iudgement.</p>
            <p>Q. Hath Chriſt then cleane forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken his Church?</p>
            <p>A. No, but is preſent with his<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 28.20 Iohn 14.16.17</note> in ſpirite, to the ende of the world.</p>
            <p>Q. What meaneth the <hi>ſitting at the right hand?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The right hand is taken for the power of God, noting that Chriſt hath all<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 28.18 Iohn 17.2 Phil. 2.9 Heb 1.3.5</note> power of his father, both of things in heauen and earth.</p>
            <p>Q. What profite commeth to vs by his aſcenſion?</p>
            <p>A. Heauen is<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 2.6</note> open to the faithful, which our ſinnes had ſhut vp, and we are aſſured that<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 8.34</note> he is our mediatour, and by this meanes<note n="c" place="margin">Iohn 7.39. &amp; 16.7</note> the holy Ghoſt is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the faithfull,</p>
            <p>Q. What teacheth the ſeuenth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle: <hi>From thence hee ſhall come to iudge both the quicke and the dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Wee learne that<note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 15 10. Apoc. 20.12</note> all men, both good and bad ſhal appeare before the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal ſeate of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Haue we any comfort or profite by this?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea, for it is happy that he which hath ſaued vs, ſhall iudge vs, for he ſhall come to acquite &amp;<note n="a" place="margin">Col. 3.4</note> glorifie the faithful, but to iudge and condemne the<note n="b" place="margin">2. The. 1.8 10</note> vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers and diſobedient.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. part.</note>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What teacheth the <hi>8.</hi> article: <hi>I beleeue in the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This article teacheth that the thirde perſon in Trinitye, GOD<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 6.63 &amp; 14.26. &amp; 16 13</note> the holy Ghoſt maketh all this profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the faithfull, and<note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.2 2. Theſ. 2.13</note> ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and<note n="c" place="margin">Iohn 3.6.8</note> regenerateth them to bee newe creatures, and a holy Church vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. part.</note>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What followeth in the <hi>9.</hi> arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle: <hi>the holy Catholike Churche, the communion of Saints?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This concerneth the fourth poynt of our faith, aſſuring vs that<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 125.1</note> GOD hath his Church on earth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What ſignifieth this woorde
<pb facs="tcp:19444:11"/> 
               <hi>Catholike?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It ſignifieth vniuerſall, noting that Chriſts Church<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 8.11 Iohn 10.16</note> is diſperſed in all places, &amp; yet but<note n="b" place="margin">Col. 1.18.24 Ephe. 4.15.16</note> one body of one head which is Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why is added the <hi>communion of Saintes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew the<note n="a" place="margin">1. Iohn 1.3</note> felowſhip which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull haue with Chriſt, and with themſelues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.3 13</note> vnitie of faith, and one mind, teaching vs<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 4.32</note> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate our graces one to another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What are the true markes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> viſible Church?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſincere<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 10.14 15</note> preaching of the worde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true miniſtring<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 20.7</note> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 12.8 Pſal. 65.1 Pſal. 18.4.4</note> prayer, &amp; diſcipline, according to the word.</p>
            <p>Q. Can there be no Church where any of thoſe doe want?</p>
            <p>A. Yes indeede: although ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed, for the woorde preached, and Sacramentes truelye miniſtred, ſhewe that there is a Churche, for they are a token of Gods face and<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 10.33 Heb. 4.12.13</note> preſence, and the printes of the<note n="b" place="margin">Ezek. 43.7</note> ſoles of his feete.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:12"/>
            <p>Q. It ſhoulde ſeeme then that the Romiſh Church is not the true Church, hauing neither the word ſincerely prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, nor the Sacramentes perfect, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſubſtance nor forme, and their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline cleane beſides the word.</p>
            <p>A. It is very true, neither can the familie of loue be the true Church, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the vocall worde, vocall prayer, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the Sacraments, and true diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline.</p>
            <p>Q. Shewe mee the meaning of the tenth article: <hi>the remiſſion of ſinnes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It aſſureth vs of the<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 32.1.2 Ephe. 1.7</note> free for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of all the ſinnes of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers, both of the fault and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Q. Doe we not merite forgiueneſſe of any one ſinne by workes?</p>
            <p>A. No certainely: but Chriſt<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 13.38.39</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is the full ſatiſfaction<note n="b" place="margin">Tit. 2.14 1. Iohn 1.7</note> for all our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Q. Are not works then needful, ſith they doe not merite?</p>
            <p>A. Yes, nothing more, firſt, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie our<note n="a" place="margin">Col. 3.17</note> thankfulneſſe and<note n="b" place="margin">1. Iohn 5.2</note> loue to
<pb facs="tcp:19444:12"/> God, &amp; to<note n="c" place="margin">Tit. 3.8 Iam. 2.18</note> proue our faith: ſecondly, to<note n="d" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.12</note> giue good example to men: thirdly, to<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 5.18 1. Cor. 10.31</note> glorifie God. Fourthly, to aſſure our conſcience that we are the ſonnes of God.</p>
            <p>Q. What teacheth the eleuenth article: <hi>the reſurrection of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. We are aſſured that the<note n="a" place="margin">Iob. 19.25</note> bodies of the faithfull ſhall riſe to behold God, and<note n="b" place="margin">Phil. 3.21</note> ſhall be made like to the glorious bodie of Chriſt, and their ſoules imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after this life<note n="c" place="margin">Eccle. 12.7 2. Cor. 5.6.7</note> returne to God.</p>
            <p>Q. Doe noe the wicked riſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo?</p>
            <p>A. Yes verily, both the<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 24.15</note> iuſt and vniuſt, the iuſt to life, and the wicked to death and iudgement.<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 5.29</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What vnderſtandeſt thou in the eleuenth article: <hi>the life euerlaſting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I vnderſtand, that after this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection there is no more cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 3 36</note> ſhall liue with Chriſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in ioy, the wicked ſhall be without Chriſt<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 25.46.</note> in eternall payne.</p>
            <p>Q. Then all this teacheth vs that the obedience of the law is onely perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:19444:13"/> by Chriſt, in whom we are freelye iuſtified through faith, wrought by Gods ſpirite, whiche geueth vs the true knowledge of GOD and his mercies in Chriſt, in whome onely wee pleaſe God, and our obedience is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <p>A. It is euen ſo.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>¶ <hi>The thirde parte</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs what dueties and thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, we owe to the Lord for this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of our redemption.</head>
            <p>Q. By what meanes is this faith &amp; obedience nouriſhed or increaſed in vs?</p>
            <p>A. By<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 10.17 Gal. 3.2</note> hearing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God, by the true<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 4.11</note> vſe of the Sacraments, &amp;<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 8.15 &amp; 10.14</note> by prayer, by which meanes alſo wee teſtifie our faith and obedience, &amp; glorify GOD.</p>
            <p>Q. Doe theſe of themſelues nouriſhe our faith?</p>
            <p>A. No, but onely<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.6 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 3.18</note> Gods ſpirit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:19444:13"/> them effectuall vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Q. Howe is our faith nouriſhed by the woorde?</p>
            <p>A. By diligent<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 10.17</note> hearing, reading, meditation, conference,<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 20 32 He. 10.24.25</note> exhortation, &amp; application of the worde, aſſuring vs of the truth therof, and of Gods promiſes,<note n="c" place="margin">Iam. 1.21</note> ſubmitting our ſelues wholly to the ſame, that it may be<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 1.16</note> a worde of power vnto ſaluation in vs.</p>
            <p>Q. What is a Sacrament?</p>
            <p>A. It is an outward<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 17.11 Rom. 4.11</note> ſeale ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the word which viſibly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth vnto vs ſpiritual things, &amp; aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth our faith of Gods promiſes decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his worde.</p>
            <p>Q. How many Sacramentes are there?</p>
            <p>A. Two: Baptiſme, and the ſupper of the Lorde.</p>
            <p>Q. How doth Baptiſme profite or nouriſh our fayth?</p>
            <p>A. Firſt, by aſſuring vs that wee are<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 6.3 1. Cor. 12.13 Gal. 3.27.</note> one with Chriſt. Secondly, that we are<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 3.3.5</note> begotten againe<note n="c" place="margin">Col. 2.11</note> from ſinne, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a new life. Thirdly, by being a pledg<note n="d" place="margin">Tit. 3.5</note> of the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes, for
<pb facs="tcp:19444:14"/> as the water cleanſeth the body, ſo our ſoules by the<note n="e" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.21.</note> blood of Chriſt are pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What profite hath our faith by the Lords ſupper?</p>
            <p>A. Euen this, that as outwardely we<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.16 &amp; 12.26</note> receiue the bread and wine to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh our bodies, ſo inwardly we receiue Chriſt by faith, euen as our own, whoſe<note n="b" place="margin">Col. 1.14.22</note> body and blood cleanſeth vs from ſin and nouriſheth vs to eternall life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Doe we receiue the very bodye and blood of Chriſt reallye in the bread?</p>
            <p>A. Nothing leſſe, but onely<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 6.63</note> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually by faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Howe ſhall wee receiue this Sacrament woorthily or profitably?</p>
            <p>A. When wee come with faith &amp; repentaunce.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How ſhall we knowe that wee come with faith?</p>
            <p>A. Firſt, if we acknowledging our owne pouertie and wants, confeſſe the mercies of God<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.24</note> with thankeſgiuing: ſecondly, when we aſſure our ſelues of the<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 26.28</note> forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes by the
<pb facs="tcp:19444:14"/> death and ſacrifice of Chriſt onely.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How ſhal we know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we come with repentance?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, if we<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28</note> examine our harts, and are truely<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 32.5.6</note> grieued for our ſinnes,<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 3.6</note> confeſſing them before God: ſecondly, when we<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 3.8</note> walke in a new life, that is, in holines to God, and true loue to our neighbour,<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 5.23 24</note> reconciling our ſelues one to another, and<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 6.14 15 Col. 3.13</note> forgiuing, that we may be forgiuen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What differeth Baptiſme fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lordes ſupper, ſith they both betoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the remiſſion of ſinnes?</p>
            <p>A. Baptiſme grafteth vs into Chriſt by regeneration in hope of remiſſion of ſinnes, the ſupper nouriſheth vs,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.13.</note> beyng grafted to feele the power of the death and reſurrection of Chriſt dayly ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening our faith into a new life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is prayer, whiche is the third meanes to increaſe our faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is to aſke all good thinges of God by faith, and to giue him thanks for all things receiued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How doth prayer nouriſh faith, when it is rather an effect or exerciſe of
<pb facs="tcp:19444:15"/> faith?</p>
            <p>A. It nouriſheth it when wee ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing aſked, doe alſo obtayne, and ſo our faith is ſtrengthened and comforted, but it is an effect of faith, becauſe where faith is,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14</note> there followeth prayer &amp; than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſgiuing.</p>
            <p>Q. What is required in true prayer?</p>
            <p>A.<note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.1 1. Tim. 2.8</note> A pure affection to GOD and his worde, a<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 32.10 Luke. 18.13</note> true feeling of our owne vnworthines, wants &amp; ſins, aſure<note n="c" place="margin">Iam 1.6 Mat. 7.7.</note> faith in the fauour and promiſes of God, and to aſke all things<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8.28</note> according to his will.</p>
            <p>Q. Are we thus prepared to prayer of our ſelues?</p>
            <p>A. No, but Gods<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.15 26 Gal. 4.6</note> ſpirite onelie teacheth vs to pray faithfully, &amp;<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 11.6</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith prayer, is not acceptable.</p>
            <p>Q. Rehearſe the Lords prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. Our father which art in heauen. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What meaneth theſe words: <hi>Our father which art in heauen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Herein God aſſureth vs, firſt of his fatherly loue to bolden vs to prayer: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, adding <hi>(in heauen)</hi> hee aſſureth
<pb facs="tcp:19444:15"/> vs of his great power, and lifteth our heartes to ſeeke him in heauen.</p>
            <p>Q. What require we in the firſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition: <hi>Halowed be thy name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We pray for grace, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wee may glorifie God in his word and workes, &amp; in all our doinges, and that his name may appeare glorious euen as it is, all vngodlines being defaced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What aſke we in the <hi>2.</hi> petition: <hi>Thy kingdome come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We pray y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God would by his word &amp;<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſpirite, gouerne &amp; increaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> number of his elect, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.24.25</note> Satans kingdom may be vtterly confounded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What aſke we in the <hi>3.</hi> peticion: <hi>Thy wil be done in earth as it is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. We pray that we may obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſigne our willes to Gods will, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 51.10 11</note> create newe heartes and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in vs by his ſpirite, and wee pray for the grace of<note n="b" place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.3</note> ſanctification, that as the<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 103.20</note> Angels in heauen doe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly pleaſe God in all motions, ſo we may ſtudy to<note n="d" place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> pleaſe him on earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What aſke we in the <hi>4.</hi> peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<pb facs="tcp:19444:16"/> 
               <hi>Geue vs this day our daily bread?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We pray that God will<note n="a" place="margin">Prou. 10.22 Deut. 28.10 12</note> bleſſe all thinges that he hath lent vs on earth, and to teach vs to<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal 145.15 16 Mat. 4.4</note> wayte on his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence in all eſtates of life, that he wil cauſe all things to ſerue our neceſſities, and the furthering of vs in our callings<note n="c" place="margin">Leuit. 26.20 26.34 Ezech. 4.16. &amp; 5.16</note> without whoſe bleſſing they al periſh and want their vſes and effects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What aſke we in the <hi>5.</hi> peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as wee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We heere call on God for the quiet eſtate of our owne conſcience, and for<note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 31.33 1. King. 8.33.36</note> the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes, to be confirmed in vs by this, that we<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 6.15 Luke 11.4</note> are willing to forgiue others, and we pray alſo that we may haue pacience to<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 5.23 Col. 3.13</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare and forgiue others offending vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What aſke wee in the <hi>6.</hi> pet. <hi>Leade vs not into temptation, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from euill?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We pray that God woulde geue vs his ſpirite to increaſe our faith, that we may<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.13</note> ouercome the motions and temptations of ſinne in vs, that ſinne
<pb facs="tcp:19444:16"/>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 6.12</note> may not reigne with vs vnto death, but that we may be freed from it more and more,<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 6.18</note> and ſet at libertie to ſerue righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Q. Doth God lead into temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that we pray he would not leade vs into temptation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God doth<note n="a" place="margin">Iam. 1.13</note> not tempt to ſinne, but he is ſaide to leade into temptation, when he<note n="b" place="margin">Eſay 63.17</note> withholdeth his graces from men, or giueth them ouer<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 1.24 26.28</note> to a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſenſe, or<note n="d" place="margin">Exo. 9.16 Rom. 9.18</note> hardeneth their heart,<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 81.12 Eſay 29.10</note> by leauing them to themſelues, but God<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 125.5 Heb. 3.13</note> ſtayeth his children from this extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whiche elſe are ready to runne to all ſinne, and therefore needfull to pray that God would not leade vs into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>Q. What meaneth this which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, <hi>For thine is the kingdome, the power and glorie, for euer and euer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It is a confirming of our faith in the power of God, to teach vs that all come of God his goodnes, and not of our ſelues, and therefore that all ſhould redound to<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 10 31.</note> his glorie by our<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 50.14 &amp; 102.18</note> thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, which is the<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 13.15.16</note> onely ſeruice that
<pb facs="tcp:19444:17"/> pleaſeth God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Now tel me briefly the ſumme of al this which thou haſt ſayd?</p>
            <p>A. Firſt, we learned by the law, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we al haue caſt off the image of God, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vnto we were created, &amp; are become by nature ſinners, children of wrath, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Gods curſe, &amp; damnation through our tranſgreſſions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we learne that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes which anſwered this curſe, and tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way damnation from the faithfull, was the onely death and ſacrifice of Chriſt, who by his ſpirite daylie reſtoreth the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God in the faithfull, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth faith, and obedience in them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we learned that by the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of faith &amp; obedience we ſhould glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God in his word, Sacramentes, &amp; by prayer, by making all our life a thankeſgiuing and prayſe vnto God for all his benefits in Chriſt. Which grace God for his Chriſtes ſake graunt to me and all his people. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>B. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:19444:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A briefe and ſhort prayer conteyning</hi> the ſumme and effect of this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Eternall God and moſt mercifull father, we thy poore ſeruaunts doe humbly acknowledge before thy preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce our manifold &amp; grieuous ſinnes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we haue broken thy moſt holy lawe, and haue iuſtly deſerued thy curſe, and eternall death and damnation: yea, and theſe our ſinnes haue growen vp with vs from our cradle, we being conceiued and borne in ſinne and iniquitie, and we dayly haue procured thy wrath againſt vs by neglecting thy wil, and following our owne corrupt wayes. So that we can finde no cauſe in our ſelues to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure thy ſauour, but are forced to flee out of our ſelues, &amp; to betake our ſelues wholly vnto thy fatherly clemencie. Wherefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (moſt gracious father) ſith in thy heauenly wiſedome, and eternall cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, thou ſhall fore appoynted thy ſonn Ieſus Chriſt to be our only mediator, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may boldly come before thee, &amp; by whoſe death &amp; cleanſing ſacrifice, it
<pb facs="tcp:19444:18"/> hath pleaſed thee to ſatiſfie thine owne iuſtice in pardoning the ſinnes of thy childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; turning away thy diſpleaſure from them, wee moſt humbly beſeeche thee in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der bowels of Ieſus Chriſt, to forgiue vs all our ſinnes, and burie them in the death and obedience of thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; we moſt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tily thanke thee (moſt louing father) for our election, creation, preſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for our redemption wrought by the death and bloodſhedding of Ieſus Chriſt &amp; for all thy aboundant mercies and graces, ſo plentifully beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs in him and for him. Alſo we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee (deare father) to giue vs thy good ſpirit to worke a liuely faith in vs, whereby the benefite of the death &amp; reſurrection of Chriſt, may bee applyed vnto vs, and become effectuall in vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may haue a true ſight and feeling of our ſinnes, and ſuch a godly ſorowe for them, as may bring foorth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce vnto ſaluation not to be repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of: ſo that we may mortifie our ſins, eſpecially, our ſeuerall ſinnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue moſt preuayled againſt vs. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that we
<pb facs="tcp:19444:18"/> may liue in all holy obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and a new life before thee on earth, that ſo we may haue comforte to our conſciences both that we are thy children, and alſo that we ſhall riſe to eternall life in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the iuſt.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, (O heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father, ſith thou haſt giuen vs thy word to teach vs all thinges needfull to ſaluation, &amp; to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct vs in thy wayes, we humbly pray thee incline our harts to imbrace &amp; prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe the ſame, make vs truely thankfull, for ſuch gracious &amp; ſoueraigne meanes of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as thou haſt offered vs, &amp; giue vs grace to vſe thy worde, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; prayer, reuerently, &amp; with faith &amp; repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, as true exerciſes &amp; teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of our faith, &amp; obedience: ſo that we may increaſe in all godlineſſe &amp; righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes before thee al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies of our life, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t theſe &amp; al other thy graces need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for vs &amp; for thy whole church, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, in whoſe name we pray together with thy whole church, &amp; for thy church as he hath taught vs ſaying. <hi>O our Father &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>O Lord increaſe our faith. Amen</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
